Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Leos, Goldie: Audio Recording, 1975 March 3 (Cassette 123A-123B)
    This interview was conducted on March 3, 1975 at the Workmen’s Circle Home for the Aged in the Bronx, New York by an unknown interviewer. Topics include Goldie Leos’ childhood in Russia; her education; her immigration to the United States (US) and first experiences in New York, New York; her marriage; her work experiences; and her views on religion. Leos discusses her childhood in Russia, including the fact that her family ran a business selling animal hides; that her father was a scholar while her mother controlled the household and business; and that she supported the family after her mother died by selling homemade candy to local businesses. She recalls her father remarrying; disliking her stepmother; the family moving to Baranovichi, Russia from Lychkovtse, Russia after her father remarried; and resenting having to continue supporting the family after they relocated. She discusses her education, including being one of only eight Jewish girls in Lychkovtse to learn Hebrew; learning Yiddish and Russian; receiving private tutoring because there was no public education for Jews; and feeling frustrated that she was not taught skills she could use in the workforce.
    Leos discusses her immigration to the US through Ellis Island in 1916, including having no immediate relatives to help support her after she arrived and feeling frustrated that she often needed to depend on distant relatives for financial support. She recalls meeting her husband in Russia and becoming reaquainted with him shortly after her arrival in the US; deciding to marry him after he cared for her during an illness; supporting him financially by taking in boarders; and rarely being apart from him until his death in the 1950s. She discusses her work experiences including sewing buttons onto children’s clothing; folding nightgowns in an unnamed factory; and managing a stationery store in the Bronx with her husband.
    Leos discusses her belief that Hasidic Jews were the happiest members of their faith; her opinion that religion strengthened her relationship with her family; and her involvement with the Zionist movement.
    Zionism and Judaism.
  - Leos, Goldie: Summary, 1975 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Levine, Sam, 1980 October 3 (Cassette 56, Box 13, Reel 56 (sides 1-2))
  - Levine, Sylvia: Audio Recording, Undated (Cassette 21)
    Sylvia Levine was born in Minsk, Russia in the late 1890s. She immigrated to the United States (US) in 1913 when she was 16 years old and worked in the garment industry. She married in 1918 and had at least one child. She was a member of an unspecified garment workers’ union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union).
    The interviewer, location, and date of this interview are unknown. The interview covers Sylvia Levine’s childhood in Minsk, Russia; her work in garment factories in New York, New York; and her husband’s life. She discusses her childhood in Minsk, including learning Yiddish and Russian from a tutor in her home and attending Hebrew school. She discusses her work in the US, including the different types of ladies’ garments she produced and production at the separate factories for each garment. She describes her first job as a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union) and struggles with her supervisor over pricing of the garments. She states that she had to stop working in 1918 when she married, but that she was able to return to work in 1931. Topics from her husband’s life include his emigration from Russia; his travels across the US in search of work; his jobs as a machinist in Detroit, Michigan and Cleveland, Ohio; his work at the Wright-Martin Aircraft Corporation in New Jersey; and his political opinions.
  - Levine, Sylvia: Transcript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Levinson, Louis, 1974 February 25 (Box 11, Reel 124 (tapes 1-2), Box 26, Cassette 124A-124B)
    Louis Levinson was born in Staryya Darohi in the Minsk region of Russia in 1907 to a Jewish family. His father immigrated to the United States before World War I and Levinson, his mother, and his sister immigrated in 1923. Levinson entered the knitting industry in the mid-1920s in order to support his family. He worked as a cutter and was quickly promoted to head cutter. He was a member of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union Local 155 until his retirement in 1972.
    This interview was conducted on February 25, 1975 at the offices of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union (ILGWU) in Manhattan, New York by an unknown interviewer. The main topics include Louis Levinson’s emigration from the Soviet Union; his work in the garment industry; and his involvement with the ILGWU Local 155. Levinson discusses his difficulty emigrating from the Soviet Union, including leaving his mother and sister behind to walk to the border of the Soviet Union and Poland; having to bribe Bolshevik border guards with his mother’s watch; sending for his mother and sister after he arrived in Poland; and his mother being shot by the Bolshevik guards. He recalls his family being arrested in Poland for being in the country illegally; receiving valid passports with the help of the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society of America; and the anti-Semitism the family encountered in Poland. He recalls his early experiences in the United States (US) including working in a dry goods store; quitting his job in order to attend a private school; his father having a stroke, leaving Levinson the sole earner of the household; and finding a job in the knitting industry.
    Levinson discusses his work as a cutter and his involvement in labor unions, including failed attempts at unionization within the knitting industry until 1933; the fight between the United Textile Workers Union and the ILGWU for control of the knitting industry; and his involvement in the ILGWU after answering a newspaper advertisement looking for members. He recalls being elected to a provisional committee at his first ILGWU meeting and increasing the number of knitting workers in attendance by asking everyone to bring a new attendee to each meeting. He discusses his political involvement within his local including being a member of the executive board; holding nearly every office and being a member of every committee; being elected as the business agent in 1943; being re-elected in every election until he retired in 1972; and feeling extremely proud that he was able to influence the knitting industry through his work in the ILGWU.
    Labor leaders |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Levitino, Frank: Audio Recording, Undated (Box 1, Cassette 155)
    Frank Levitino was born in a small town in Sicily, Italy around 1904. His father immigrated to the United States (US) a year after Levitino was born. Levitino and his mother immigrated to the US in 1921. The family lived lived on York and Main Streets in the Fulton Landing neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. In Italy, he and his mother worked on a farm. In the US, his mother did not work outside of the home. His father cleaned in a factory. Levitino’s first two jobs in the US were in a can factory on Front Street in Brooklyn and in a sugar factory. He served in the United States Army Coast Artillery Corps for one year in the early 1920s. In 1927 he started working for the New York City Department of Sanitation, driving a truck and working as a welder in the mechanic bureau. He was a member of the International Union of Operating Engineers. He retired in 1972.
    Levitino married in 1930 and had three children. The family lived in the same building as Levitino’s parents in Fulton Landing.
    This interview was conducted by Joan Granucci on April 9 of an unspecified year. The location is likely the Congress of Italian Americans Organization (CIAO) in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Frank Levitino’s working life the United States (US) and his family. Levitino discusses his first jobs in the US, including the fact that the change from farm work to factory work did not bother him; that he was happy to be in America and have a job; and the poor working conditions and lack of unions in the factories. He discusses his work for the New York City Department of Sanitation, including first driving a truck; testing to become a welder in the mechanic bureau; and repairing motor blocks. He discusses failed attempts at unionization in the Department of Sanitation and the success of the International Union of Operating Engineers in 1966.
    International Union of Operating Engineers.; New York (N.Y.). Department of Sanitation.; Sanitation workers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Welders (Persons) |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Levintino, Frank: Subject Cards, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Lewis, George, Undated (Cassette Missing)
  - Lewis, Ivan, Undated (Cassette 217 & 217A, Box 18)
    Ivan Lewis was interviewed at his home in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The date and interviewer are unknown. Main topics of discussion include Lewis’ life in Trinidad and Tobago; his social life in New York City between the 1930s and the time of the interview; and politics at the time of the interview. Lewis discusses his early life in Trinidad and Tobago, including his family being wealthy and his father owning three estates; his father dying when Lewis was six; having three sisters and one brother; and attending high school. He mentions his immigration to the United States, including his first impressions of New York City; immigrating in order to continue his education; living with his aunt in Manhattan until he married in 1927; attending night school to become an auto mechanic; and being in awe of the New York City Subway and elevators. He discusses his participation in the social scene and leisure activities in New York City, including attending the Cotton Club every Thursday; socializing with his neighbors on the street and in cafes. He also recalls the existence of a large West Indian community in both Brooklyn and Harlem. He lists former employers, including Eastern Foundry in Trinidad and Tobago; and in the US, working for an unnamed spring manufacturer; Bethlehem Steel Corporation; and Wilson Slaughterhouse in Manhattan, New York. He discusses working as an elevator operator until his retirement. Lewis mentions that he was a member of an unnamed elevator operators’ union and that the strikes were never violent. He discusses politics at the time of the interview including feeling disillusioned with politics; supporting Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. and thinking Powell was killed because of his influence in the community; and believing that the events of the Watergate Scandal were not uncommon within politics.
    See also: Family; Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York,New York and the United States; and Neighborhood.
    Cotton Club.; Elevator operators |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Life Before Immigration or Migration, Undated (Cassette Missing, Box 16)
    Joseph Savio was born on May 14, 1891 in a small town in Sicily, Italy. He was one of six children. His father was a shoemaker and a landowner. Savio attended school in Italy for three years and for a short time in the United States (US) after his immigration with his family in 1901. He worked as a delivery boy and a cutter in the glove industry.
    Mrs. Sunderman was born in Frankfurt, Germany in the late 19th century. Her parents owned a hosiery store. She married and had one daughter. Her husband died in 1938 and she immigrated to the United States (US) two years later. In the US she worked as a housekeeper, companion, and seamstress.
    Several other intervieews also contribute to the compilation.
    This recording contains excerpts of different interviews, all of which focus on discussions of immigrants’ and migrants’ lives before they came to New York, New York. The volume and sound quality of this recording fluctuate between excerpts. The excerpts include discussion of life in the narrators’ places of origin, including education, ethnic relations, class differences, major occupations, and the differences in opportunities for men and women. A significant number of narrators address the Jewish experience, including the relationship between Jewish communities living alongside other religious communities in the same area; and anti-Semitism before and during World War II. Narrators also discuss their reasons for immigration or migration and the sequence of family members’ immigration or migration.
    See also: Brackett, Mary; Cappeletti, Caroline Lavecchia; Cohen, Rose; Fox, Abe; Gelo, Grace; Richards, Evadni; Robinson, Irene; Savio, Joseph; Sunderman, [Unknown Woman]; and Unger, Margareta.
  - Little, Mary, Undated (Cassette 208, Box 18, Box 2, Reel 208 (side 2))
    Mary Little was born on January 1, 1924 in Washington, North Carolina. She was the second of four children. Her parents worked in a tobacco warehouse in Greenwood, North Carolina. Her father died when Little was very young. Little graduated from high school in Washington. She moved to New York, New York in 1945, where she worked in various garment factories. She had two children, a daughter who became a registered nurse and a son who became an actor and a dancer.
    The interviewer, date, and location of the interview are unknown. This interview covers Mary Little’s childhood and adolescence in Washington, North Carolina, her migration to New York, New York in 1945, and her life in New York City up to the time of the interview. Little describes her childhood as split between Washington, where she was born, and the family’s farm, which her mother inherited from her grandfather, a former slave. She discusses her work tending to cotton and peanut plants on the family farm and the differences in the chores she and her brothers were assigned. She describes her first job attending to the mother of a Mrs. Legette, a member of a prominent white family in Washington. She focuses on how she integrated with the family, noting that Mrs. Legette threatened to withdraw her membership from the local Presbyterian church if it did not allow Little to attend with the family. She discusses the open racial prejudice and segregation that permeated the southern United States (US); the jobs her brothers acquired; her marriage; and her desire to visit New York.
    Little explains that she moved to New York in 1945 and adapted to Manhattan while living with her relatives. She describes working in a variety of garment factories, always moving on to a new factory when she had learned everything she could at the old one. She emphasizes the differences between living in the northern and southern United States, noting the differences in the ways that men treated women; the differences in family values; and the differences between living in the southern countryside and living in a northern city. Little ends the interview by talking about her children’s occupations, focusing specifically on her son’s acting career.
  - Loskowitz, Charles: Audio Recording, 1973 March 21 and March 26 (Cassette 22 & 23)
    Charles Loskowitz was born in Russia in the 1890s. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1904 with his mother and two siblings, his father and two older siblings having immigrated earlier. The family settled in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. His father worked as a carpenter in Russia and as a presser in a dress factory in the US. His mother did not work outside the home. Loskowitz graduated from Primary School 156 in Brooklyn and worked while attending a private high school. He worked in the Canadian Car and Foundry Company’s ammunition plant in New Jersey until it was destroyed in 1917. He worked for Remington Arms in Bridgeport, Connecticut. He joined the US Army in 1917 and was stationed in England, France, and Germany. He was discharged at the end of World War I.
    Loskowitz worked as a letter carrier for the United States Postal Service for 27 years, retiring in 1946. He was a member of the National Association of Letter Carriers and the American Legion. He married in 1917. He and his wife had three children before divorcing in the 1940s.
    This interview was conducted by Mary B. Alexander at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York on March 21 and March 26, 1973. The interview covers Charles Loskowitz’s childhood in Russia and the United States (US), his immigration to the US, his working life, and his marriage. Loskowitz compares his life in Russia with his life in US, including his surprise at the differences in the family’s living arrangements; his confusion over laundry hanging outdoors on clotheslines; and his experiences at school. He discusses his work at the Canadian Car and Foundry Company’s munitions plant in New Jersey; the explosion at the plant in 1917; and his recuperation at a stranger’s home.
    Loskowitz discusses not being interested in joining immigrant organizations but in organizations related to his experiences in the US, in particular his occupation as a letter carrier and his Army service during World War I which led to his joining the National Association of Letter Carriers and the American Legion. He discusses his marriage at length, describing his unhappiness in the marriage; the arrangement of the marriage by his mother and her cousin; and his children’s relationship with him and his wife after the divorce. He describes his wife changing her and their children’s last name to Laskoe in order to Americanize it and his neutral feelings about this change. He explains reasons immigrants would change their names once in the US.
    Other topics include his children and their occupations; his opinions on Judaism and Catholicism; sports he played as a child; and songs he would sing with his family around the dinner table.
    National Association of Letter Carriers (U.S.); Divorce |z United States |v Anecdotes.; Kingsland Explosion, Lyndhurst, N.J., 1917
  - Loskowitz, Charles: Summary, 1973 March 21 and March 26 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Lynch, Gwendaline, 1974 April 9 (Cassette Missing)
  - Magliacano, Joseph: Audio Recording, 1973 March 27 (Cassette 146)
    Joseph Magliacano was born in 1897 in San Marco in the province of Salerno, Italy. He immigrated to the United States in 1913. He lived in the Bronx, New York; the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York; and Newark, New Jersey. He graduated from an unspecified chiropractic college in New York City (likely the Carver Chiropractic College) in 1924. He was a member of the American Labor Party, an unspecified barbers’ union in New York, and the executive committee of the New Jersey State Congress of Industrial Organizations. He was an organizer for a number of labor unions, including the United Textile Workers of America and the United Shoe Workers’ Union. He was a founder of the United Furniture Workers of America and remained with that organization until his retirement.
    Magliacano married in 1931. His wife was Jewish and was born in Bronxville, New York. She was a member of the United Shoe Workers Union and an organizer for an unspecified Jewish women’s organization. They had at least one child together.
    This interview was conducted on March 27, 1973 by Joan Granucci at Joseph Magliacano’s home in New Jersey. The interview covers Magliacano’s early life in Salerno, Italy; his immigration to the United States (US); his varied career in the American labor movement; and his personal life. Magliacano discusses his childhood in San Marco in the province of Salerno; his family; and his immigration to the US. He discusses working as a barber in New York City; being a member of an unspecified barbers’ union; attending an unspecified school in Manhattan (likely the Rand School of Social Science); and attending and graduating from an unspecified chiropractic college in Manhattan (likely the Carver Chiropractic College) He discusses hitchhiking to Chicago, Illinois after graduation to attend a postgraduate course at an unspecified chiropractic college there; learning that the barbers’ union was holding its national convention in Indianapolis, Indiana and deciding to attend; and deciding to rejoin the labor movement while at the convention. He discusses joining the Italian American anti-Fascist movement in New York and this decision leading to his becoming an organizer for different labor unions, including the United Textile Workers of America (UTW) and the United Shoe Workers’ Union (USWU). He discusses his work as an organizer; his involvement as a representative of the UTW in the textile workers’ strike in Passaic, New Jersey in 1926; his work with an unspecified relief organization aiding striking coal miners in Pennsylvania, West Virginia, and Kentucky in 1928 and 1929; and his work for the USWU between 1929 and 1932. Other topics include Magliacano’s opinion of the Catholic Church; his travel to the Soviet Union in the late 1960s and early 1970s as a member of a trade union delegation; a visit to San Marco in 1961 and the changes there since his childhood; and his life at the time of the interview.
    See also: Leisure; Politics; and Unionization.
    Related Archival Materials
    For more information about Joseph Magliacano see the Joseph Magliacano Papers and Photographs collection, call number WAG.223.
    United Furniture Workers of America.; United Textile Workers of America.; Barbers |x Labor unions.; Textile Workers' Strike, Passaic, N.J., 1926.
  - Magliacano, Joseph: Summary, 1973 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Malkind, Sylvia: Audio Recording, Undated (Cassette 24)
    Sylvia Malkind was born in an unspecified European country (likely Russia) and immigrated to the United States as a young child. She married and had children. She was an organizer for the Cleaners and Dyers Union.
    The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. The interview covers Sylvia Malkind’s early life in Europe and her working life. The interview is a somewhat hard to follow as Malkind jumps from one topic to another. She discusses her family’s first apartment in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York, including the fact that there was no heat, electricity, or running water. She discusses her first job in a garment factory; her efforts to educate the workers as to their rights; the foreman’s attempts to keep her away from the workers by moving her to officework; and her decision to leave this job. She explains that she worked for a time as a social worker, including at the Immigrant Aid Society and then the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society (HSIAS). She recounts moving into the position of social worker at HSIAS after the death of the previous social worker, despite having little experience. She discusses working for a time as a field worker for the Jewish Big Brothers and Big Sisters.
    Malkind discusses her work as an organizer for the Cleaners and Dyers Union and the women she tried to recruit into the union. She describes the working conditions in the dry cleaning stores in New York City and the women who worked in these stores. She discusses the difficulty she faced in attempting to organize these stores; the reluctance of the women to participate in union meetings; her attempts to make the meetings more interesting; and her the entertainment she arranged in order to interest them in the union. She discusses the way in which she was nominated for her position of organizer by people in her neighborhood and her five re-elections to that position.